Hi everyone, this is Andy with
Blungo.com and in this video I'm going to
show you how to automatically
create a related record using a
function in Zoho CRM. For this example,
when a deal is moved to
closed won, it will create a related
record in the jobs module. In the
description, you can find a
blog post with the written step-by-step
tutorial, as well as the code that
we're going to use today.
Alright, let's get started. There are
two ways to create a related records.
The first one is to use
the workflow action, create a
related records, but it is limited on what
information you can pass to
the related record. Then the ways to
use a function, and that's how we're
going to do it in this tutorial.
This is the deal we're going to use.
And if we scroll down, we can see that
we have these three
fields that we would like to pass to
the related record. It is a drop-down
field, a date field,
and a user field. So besides creating
the record, we're going to copy some
information as well.
The first thing we have to do is
go to the CRM setup, and then open
the module where the
related record is going to be created.
In my case, I want to create a job
after a deal is won,
so I'm going to open
the jobs module, which
is a custom module.
And open the layout.
Here, I already have the fields that
need to be mapped from the deal,
but I'm going to add one more
field that will link
these two modules.
It is a lookup field. So
let's drag and drop it.
And in this new window,
let's name it, deal related.
The module lookup
is going to be deals.
And the related list
is going to be jobs.
Click on Done.
Okay, we have all
the fields we need,
so let's save this
layout.
Now we have to
create a function.
In this tab, I already have the
functions page open.
We are going to
create a new function.
Let's add a name
and a display name.
The category is going
to be automation.
Click on create.
The code is in the blog post.
I have it open right here.
Scroll down until
you find the code.
Select it.
And copy it.
Back to the function.
And paste it right here.
Next, we have to
add an argument.
So click on edit argument
and add deal_id as a string.
This is the information
that will be passed to the
function from the workflow
that we're going to create later.
Click on save.
And now I'm going to
explain what the function does.
But before I do that, I
wanted to mention that
we have created a Zoho
one course for admins.
So if you're interested, check
out the link in the description.
So the function first gets the deal
information based on the Deal ID.
Then it grabs the
information located in the
different deal fields that
we want to copy to the job.
In this case, estimator,
type and closing date.
The estimator is a user field.
That's why we need to get the ID.
Then it is creating the job record name,
which is the word job and the deal name.
Then it maps all the fields
from the deal to the job record.
Finally, it creates the record.
You have to make sure
that you're using the right
API names in the function.
The two most important
fields are deal_related,
which is the lookup field we added
before and jobs, which is the module API
name. To find them,
go to the API names in the CRM settings.
These are all the module API names.
If we scroll down,
we can see the jobs module
and on the right, the API name
to find API names
just open the module.
Here is the
deal_related API name.
You can switch to all
their modules with this filter.
Okay, back to the function.
At this point, you can
click on save and execute
if you want to
test this function.
In my case, I know it works.
So I'm just going to save it.
All right, the function is ready.
So now we need to create a workflow.
I have the workflow section open
on this tab. Let's create a new rule.
The module is deals.
Add a name.
And click on next.
Here, select record action.
Edit.
Specific field gets modified.
When the stage is modified to.
The value.
Closed Won.
Next
this rule is going
to apply to all deals.
Next
and the action is
going to be function.
In this box, click on functions.
And click on configure next
to the function we just created.
This is the parameter we're passing
to the function. So press the pound key,
module is deals. And field is Deal
ID. And click on save and associate.
The workflow is ready. So let's save it.
All right, we can now test
if this automation works.
Let's go back to the deal
and refresh the page.
On the related list, we
can now see the jobs tab.
Okay, let's move the deal
to the closed won stage,
which will trigger the workflow.
And refresh the
page one more time.
And now we can see that
there's a record right there.
So let's click on the list.
The job record has been
created.
And the name is job
plus the deal name.
Let 's open it.
And the three fields have
been mapped correctly.
All right, I hope you
guys enjoyed the video.
And if you did, please
click the like button.
If you're a Zoho admin
and would like to learn
more about how to integrate
the different Zoho apps,
we made a Zoho one course where
we go over how to configure and
integrate the top 10
most used Zoho one apps. Check
out the link in the description for more
information.
Thanks for watching.