Hi everyone, this is Andy with Blungo.com
and in this video we're going to do
a quick overview of Zoho Tables.
This is like a spreadsheet on steroids.
You will be able to
create and connect tables
so they share
information as well as set
up automations and a lot more.
Alright let's get started.
Keep in mind that Zoho Tables is in
beta at the moment of the recording
of this video.
So, some features might change by
the time that the version 1 is released.
You can request early access
using the link in the description.
This is a base that we use to
track and analyze user feedback.
This base contains two tables.
User feedback and feedback analysis.
And each table contains views
that we're going to review later.
As you can see it is very similar to a
spreadsheet but there are some extra
fields like the attaching ones.
To add a new field, click on
the plus button and select one.
We have many options here like AutoNumber,
Collaborator, Formula, Rating but
two really important
fields are the link field
that will let you connect
tables and the lookup
field that will
allow you to bring
information to a table
from another table.
Let's add a date field.
Now we can select
dates on this field.
You can also use the
Manage Fields button.
In case your table has many fields
and you want to quickly make changes or
add new fields.
If you want to delete a record, just
click on this arrow and then on Delete.
To add a record to this
table, we have several options.
The first one is to click on an
empty cell and type the information in.
The second way is to click
on the Add a Record button.
Then just complete
the fields and that's it.
The record will be added.
The last one is by using a form.
This table already has a form but later
on I will show you how to create one.
Under Views, we can see Feedback Form.
Let's open it.
Here we can edit the form.
For example if we need to change
the name of the fields or hide fields.
But the cool part is
that you can click on
Get Form URL and
then if you open the link,
it will bring you to the form that you
can use to add records to your table.
You can share these form with others
so they can add records without having
to open the table.
Before we continue,
I wanted to mention
that we have created a
Zoho one course for admins.
So, if you're interested, check
out the link in the description.
Ok. Let's close this.
And this.
Up here we can see that there is
another table called Feedback Analysis.
This table is similar to the
other one but has more fields.
Like a drop down called Category
and a multi select called Tags.
But it also has this
link field that links
this table with the
user feedback table.
And also lookup field
that is showing the
feedback text from
the other table as well.
This table has different views.
The deadlines view is a calendar
view that shows when the records do.
The grey boxes are the records.
You can click on any of them to
see more information about the record.
Another view is called Actionable
Feedback which is very similar to the
default view but it is filter.
It is only showing records where
the actionable field is checked.
Finally, we have the Stacked by
Category view which is a kanban view.
You can move a record from one column
to another one by dragging and dropping it.
To create a new
view, click on this plus
button and then select the
view that you want to create.
Here's where you
can set up a new form.
Keep in mind that the views you
create here are for this table only.
OK, let's select Gallery.
And the view has been created.
On the side panel,
you can drag and drop
more fields that will
show on the cards.
To delete a view, click on the
three dots and then on delete.
If you want to add a new table
to your base, click on this button.
Then select if you want to start
with an empty table or import a file.
You can import spreadsheets and
CSV files that you already have from your
computer or from the cloud.
Let's go back and create a blank table.
Here you can start adding new
records and link them to the other tables.
To delete a table, click on
this arrow and then on delete.
On the right side, we
can see the log button.
This panel shows
all the changes made
to this table in a
chronological order.
The next button is the
Automations button.
It allows you to create basic automations
within the tables in this space.
For example, this one sends
email when a record is created.
Other actions are to create a
record and to update a record.
I think the list of possible
automations will increase over time.
If you want to share this space, click
on the Share button and either share
via email or by selecting
the coloborators in your team.
If you click on the tables logo,
you will land on the home screen.
Here you can find your bases.
In my case, I have two.
You can add more
bases with this button.
One extra option that
we have here is templates.
There are templates for many use
cases on this section that Zoho included.
So you don't have to start
building bases from scratch.
The last thing I want
to show you is that
you can have multiple
workspaces you need to.
If you're part of multiple teams, each
team can have its own workspace.
You can manage workspace
members by clicking here.
Alright, I hope you
guys enjoyed the video
and if you did, please
click the like button.
If you're a Zoho admin
and would like to learn
more about how to
integrate different Zoho apps,
we made a Zoho one
course where we go over
how to configure and
integrate the top 10
most used Zoho one apps.
Check out the link in the
description for more information.
Thanks for watching.