Programming is only one part
of our job as software engineers.
In addition to programming the
feature that we're being asked to build,
we are responsible for creating
systems that will last, that will stand the
test of time.
And there's many effective ways
of doing that as software engineers.
There's code reviews, there's challenging
your designer, your product owner,
there's testing, there's
working with automated tests,
there's continuous integration,
continuous delivery, there's DevOps,
there's effective communication,
there's time management.
There's so many
things that are also
part of our job that
are not programming.
But having said all that, programming
is a part of our job and it is an
important part of our job.
How do we get better
at programming?
How do we hone the skill that
is typing code to solve problems?
This video looks at that.
Let's get into it.
Step one, learn your
programming language really well.
I advise you to take a structured
way at learning the language.
Make sure you make a plan, you set
your goals and you work through that plan
step by step.
Even if you've been working with a
programming language for quite a while,
even for years,
it makes sense to get
back to that knowledge
to make sure you know
your tool really well.
You won't accidentally
reach for external tools,
whereas you already had the
tool in your language all along.
Start with syntax essentials.
Go through the reference guide and
learn about all the standard objects,
the expressions, the operators, what
is an expression versus a statement.
Go through variables, conditionals,
functions, modules, and then
data structures, data types.
How do they relate?
Again, it's your toolbox.
You have to be aware what's in your
toolbox, so you won't accidentally reach
for external things when you've
had this tool in your toolbox all along.
I would advise everybody to scroll
through the entire reference manual for
your language
to just know about everything.
You don't have to know all
the little details of everything.
You have to be aware of what
features your language offers,
because the moment you're aware
you run into a problem in the future,
you know exactly what to search for.
And, that is a really important
skill as a programmer,
to be aware what is there and
to be able to search for that thing,
because you won't remember
all these tiny syntax details.
That there's no use in
investing so much time in that.
There's use in knowing what is
available, you know what to search for,
and then you can quickly solve
your problem in the right way.
The point is not to use everything
that's available in your language.
The point is to be
aware of what's available.
In fact, I would go further and say,
"I would stay away from the
obscure features of your language."
Every language has
some things that if you
look at the broader
programming community,
people are using less or not at all.
You know, language is
a design exercise as well.
Language designers didn't
make a perfect language either.
They have some parts that they're
happy with and some parts that they're
less happy with,
and the community generally evolves
thought around this kind of thing.
So it's good to be
aware of that and to say,
"Okay, this is a less used feature
of the language in our industry.
I'm going to steer clear from it.
I'm going to sort of deny list it in
my head and try and not use it."
Knowing what's
available prevents you
from needing Stack
Overflow for everything.
It prevents you from random
searches that don't make sense,
and it prevents you from
adding dependencies
that you wouldn't
otherwise need.
It makes you write code the way the
average person in the industry with that
same language would,
which is a good thing in the long term.
When you haven't picked any
obscure features of your language,
it means maintainability is higher.
It means code quality is higher.
It means onboarding goes faster.
It means a lot of positive things.
Step two, learn the frameworks
and the libraries that you're using.
I've seen many people who Stack
Overflow their way through their career,
and nowadays it's Copilot and
ChatGPT, but it's very similar.
It's an external tool that
helps you solve a problem.
Whereas if you would simply have
the knowledge of your language,
your framework, and your library,
then you wouldn't need some
other tool or some search engine
to come up with the solution for you.
You would know exactly
how it should be solved,
and then you can
instruct an AI, or then
you can look up
official documentation.
There's nothing wrong
with searching itself,
but it's often a sign of not
knowing how to solve your problem.
And that really needs to be solved first.
You really need to think
through, "Will I solve this problem?
How do I even get started on this problem?
What is this problem composed of?".
Otherwise, these searches will
not help you in the right direction.
They will give you random
results, unpredictable results,
simply outdated or wrong
results, is all possible.
Let's look at one.
I'm using Luxon,
the date library, and I
needed to figure out
how to add a month.
This is my search engine, Kagi,
and it gave me no useful results.
I tried a few other ones,
Google, for example.
It also didn't give me useful results.
They both give me this bug that's there.
Okay, I'm not interested in that.
It gives me documentation,
and when I open
it, it seems to be
outdated documentation,
and also it's not telling me everything.
It's not answering my specific question.
Whereas if I would simply go to
the official documentation of Luxon,
and I would have
read this once, then I
would know there is a
math feature available,
and I would simply be able
to add via the plus method.
This is an example of
the official documentation
having a really nice structured
way of explaining things, and
also explaining which units
can we use to use math,
and what do we need to pay attention to?
If I get this StackOverflow answer,
then yes, they might also have
written this essay for an answer,
but will it tell you that months vary
because there are different lengths
and quarters and all these kind of details?
And if you would have read
this documentation just once,
you would have remembered that doing
math on datetime objects is an option,
and maybe you won't remember
the exact syntax, but that's fine.
You can now search for that.
You can use a very specific
term to open up the documentation,
scroll through the math
thing, and then you know,
or you could search
for Luxon datetime math,
and it would immediately
pop up the right page
because you know what you're looking for.
And in the case of React,
make sure you read the documentation,
the reference on all the hooks.
Yes, all of them.
Even if you won't need
half of them, that's okay.
You can't predict whether you might
need them a few months from now.
So it's important
to again be aware
of what's there,
what's available to you.
So you know exactly what to search for.
So search will be helpful.
Otherwise, search will be unhelpful.
You'll get random StackOverflow answers.
You'll have difficulty coming
up with which exact keywords
are you going to search for.
How are you going to
explain the problem to an AI
if you don't understand the problem first?
Reading official documentation,
like from your language
or framework or your
library, is an underrated
skill nowadays.
I think it's a very important thing
to be aware of what tools you have.
Yes, StackOverflow has its use.
AIs have their uses, but
it's not structuring your code.
It's not seeing the bigger picture.
That's not within the
capability of these things.
You have to do that.
You are responsible
for that as a programmer.
My next tip is to
learn how to approach
programming problems
in a structured way.
I've talked about this before in my
video on problem solving for coders.
It boils down to analyzing
the problem, making a plan,
and all of that before you start typing.
Watch that video if you want to learn more.
It also involves learning the common
design pattern that are out there.
And you could achieve this by reading
books, like the Gang of Four book,
but I personally don't enjoy reading
the Java language as it was in 1994.
That's quite far from
people's realities nowadays.
And there's alternative, modern
approaches like patterns.dev website.
They have, if you're
in a JavaScript,
a React context, of
course there's alternatives
if you're in a different language,
but this is a free e-book
and it has modern patterns.
explained in a really nice way.
There's, if you want to, some
of it has overlap with the book,
but half of it isn't in the book
and half of it is front end specific.
And that is really where
this kind of thing shines.
This is a website so
it's being kept up to date.
You can also download it as a
PDF or e-book or whatever you need.
The important thing is
it will not get out of date
because there's people
committed to this kind of thing.
Another way is to approach
problems together with people,
to find opportunities to
problem solve together.
Maybe you can pair program the first hour
of a new user story that
one of your team members
is picking up because the
moment you start getting into
somebody else's thinking,
somebody else's approach
to problems, you learn a lot of new things.
You're effectively
getting a sort of mentoring
and the knowledge
sharing in your team
starts to flow more readily.
I've just talked about
doing some analysis
and making a plan
before you start typing.
Why not add a review phase?
It only has to take five or 10 minutes.
In between your plan is
finished and you start typing.
Why not have a video conference or
two people behind the same computer,
chatting about the problem and
how you want to approach the solution.
This is how you learn about the others,
train of thought when solving a problem.
The more exposed to other
approaches to problems you are,
the more you will
have available in
your toolbox for
future problems as well.
My next tip is to learn your editor
or IDE and your terminal really well
because it's the best way to get
quick feedback from your tools.
You're about to make this error.
You're about to introduce this bug.
This thing might not work.
You have forgotten to include this file.
That's the kind of thing that the
quicker you get your feedback,
the less bugs will end up in production.
The more high code quality
you will be able to deliver.
The quicker you can get your
thoughts into your keyword,
so to say, the less mistakes you will make.
My tip is to pick one editor,
one IDE with your team
and to stick with it, to
learn everything about it.
For example, Visual Studio
Code has this tips and tricks page
and it has a lot of things that
if you never went through this,
if you're just a new user or you're
only using the typing code feature,
it will give you a lot of
hints on what's available.
The command palette
will make you a lot faster.
These are the default shortcuts.
I advise you to literally print out
this shortcut sheet for your OS
and put it next to your
computer for a week.
Yes, it will hurt in the beginning,
but at some point you'll
just know all the shortcuts.
You can throw this sheet
away and you're a ton faster
and it's more comfortable working
with the tools you're working with.
There's all kinds
of features that your
editor has that you're
probably not using.
And exploring all of
these and slowly deciding,
"I want to use this because
this is an action I'm doing often,"
is a sort of automation
mindset that will, again,
it will improve your life,
it will make you quicker.
There's an integrated command
line, there's a status bar,
there's all kinds of features here.
IntelliSense, what can it actually do?
Peak, go to definition, go to references.
There's many, many features here.
I have VS Code both on my
private laptop and my work laptop
and I like to keep
these things in sync
so that I always have
the same shortcuts,
I have the same development environment
and when I need to
install a new laptop or
whatever, I have
this available instantly
and I have my environment
set up really quickly.
And my last tip is to have pet
projects to learn a specific skill.
I love having pet projects,
I have a lot of them.
It's a great way to learn new things.
There's a danger with pet projects though.
Make sure you don't over commit.
It's just a pet project and there's
a real chance you won't finish it.
So you'd better come up with some idea
that you're okay not
finishing, especially
if you want to
learn a specific skill
from your pet project.
Make sure you prioritize.
Do you want to have
the app or the thing built?
Do you want to have it finished?
Or do you want to learn the skill?
It's the same things with books.
I feel okay reading a book for only half.
If I have thought
of, before I read the
book, before I start
reading the book,
I want to learn this one thing.
That's why I read this book.
If I'm halfway and
I've learned the thing,
I will feel okay
putting the book down.
The same with the pet project.
If you're in it for a specific skill,
you can ignore the pet project.
You don't have to feel bad for that.
An example from my own history
is when I wanted to learn the MUI,
the Material UI React Component Framework.
I wanted to see how
composable it actually was.
So I started my pet project.
I conceived of an ID.
I had the recipe manager 5000
because we were doing meal planning at home
and we were struggling
with syncing our recipes
that we had a lot
of that we wanted to
reuse, but they're all
in different sources.
And we also had a problem
with our shopping list.
We wanted to automatically add a
whole bunch of things to our shopping list.
So I thought, why not make an app for that?
And this turned out to be an app
that we're actually using nowadays.
But it didn't start that way.
It started out as me wanting to figure out.
how does MUI work?
But I got sidetracked.
We figured out when using it
that we would need authentication,
we would need to
actually host it, we would
need to do this and
this and this and this
and that's not where I
was learning anymore.
So this is where I lost a bit of
motivation for my pet project
because I was initially in it to learn MUI.
And once I had achieved that goal,
there was less motivation
for me to continue.
But in this case, we ended
up actually using the app.
And now there's conflicting goals.
There's me wanting to learn some
stuff, which was at some point achieved.
I know now of the composability
and the limits of MUI.
And there's the goal of
this app needs to work.
And I also needed to learn
something like Firebase
and what to do to make
sure authentication works,
to make sure we could
host the backend database.
And that kind of stuff,
that was conflicting.
And if you're not in it to
manage that kind of stuff as well,
then you don't want to turn
your app into a real use case app.
Then you're not in it for that.
Then you're just in it for learning it.
So that you stop halfway your
project while it's not finished is fine
if you've achieved your learning goal.
To summarize, take a methodical
approach to learning the language framework
and library as you're working with.
Make a plan, go through
the plan step by step.
Make sure you read official docs.
Stay away from Stack Overflow,
Copilot or ChatGPT to learn new things.
They will be getting
your stuff working,
but they will not
teach you new skills.
They will not teach you how a
library is supposed to be used,
how, what a natural use case
of this framework or language is.
In my experience, many
times you need Stack Overflow,
you don't understand
the problem well enough.
And lastly, make sure you collaborate
with other people as much as possible.
Pair programming,
code reviewing, all
these things will make
you talk about code
that will give you insights into the
other person's problem solving skills
and the way they approach problems.
And this will make you learn a lot quicker.
And that's it.
I hope you liked it.
I hope this was useful.
If you have any
thoughts or if you have
an idea for a specific
video in the future,
please let me know in the
comments and subscribe.
Thank you very much for watching.