I want to share with
you what to me is the
most effective method
of learning any skill
and how using it has changed my life.
But first, we need to go back to 2013.
At that time, I was about to
finish my bachelor's in biology,
and one thing that I already knew
back then is that I didn't want to spend
the rest of my career
working in a lab. Therefore, I started
looking for masters that would allow
me to do a career shift.
So I started checking for engineering
programs, and I ended up in the
website of this program
that looked perfect to me, except
for one thing, and is that they required
coding skills,
which I completely lacked at the
moment, and actually they wanted to test
those coding skills
before accepting you into the master.
So of course, at that moment, given I
had zero knowledge
in coding, I decided to apply for it?
Yes, I applied for it. In that moment,
something changed.
It was like a switch had been flipped
in my brain, and it's something that I
continued to experience
many times as I grew older, and
led me to believe that I was capable of
learning anything.
This thing that happened to me, I
call it pressurized passion. Basically,
As soon as I applied for that program,
my brain became like a sponge, and it
started absorbing
everything related to coding. I was
following every single online course I
could find about coding
from Stanford and MIT, and I was
going through all the lessons, taking notes,
and doing every
single exercise I could find in their
curriculum. Basically, I was spending
every day and night
thinking about coding, and my brain
somehow started learning faster than
ever done before.
I was seeing very quick progress,
which kept me motivated to keep learning
and keep taking
courses, and after two months of
being in this pressurized passion mode,
I took the test, which I passed,
and I entered the master's I wanted.
There's a problem with this method,
is that you need
two things to make it
work. One of them is
some sort of pressure,
and the other thing is passion to feel it.
And the problem is that as time
goes by, one or the other
tend to get lower, and eventually it
reaches a point where basically, that
topic, at some point,
you find like the most interesting
topic on the planet, and you could absorb
anything related to it,
All of a sudden you find it boring,
and you just couldn't care less about it,
and this is also what
happened to me.
Now, if you want to solve
this problem, you need to
understand how to boost
both of those elements. The first
one is the passion. If you want to do
something, you first need
to have some sort of interest in it,
and the best way to create that passion
is by starting with
why. You should ask yourself, "Why
do I want to learn that skill? What do I
want to take out of it?"
And basically, as time goes by, you
need to keep on reminding yourself of
the answers of those
questions to keep that passion and
motivation alive. The second element is
the pressure. You need to
somehow feel the need of delivering
on something to someone, and the trick
here is that that need should
be enough, that if you don't deliver
need, you kind of feel bad about it,
but at the same time,
you don't want that need to be too
high, because if so, the pressure will be
so high that basically,
it will be compromising, and also
you will not move forward. So, the trick
here is to find the right
balance between having a bit of
pressure, but just not too much. So, let me
give you another example here.
This case, we're in 2016. I already
graduated from my masters, and I was
already working on my
first engineering job. And at this
point, I'm still passionate about coding,
but to be honest, I don't
have the energy anymore to go through
all those tutorials, like I used to do
three years before.
Now, one day, in the project I was
working on, we're looking at one of the
measurement tools,
and we're thinking, "How could we
automate one of the steps of that tool by
using image processing?"
Now, usually, we just go to the
coding expert of our team and ask him to
create an algorithm to automate
that step. In this case, he was out
of office for the coming two weeks, so
actually, we could not really do that.
In that moment, I decided I wanted
to try to impress my colleagues, and I
told them that probably I could
do it, and actually, we didn't really
have to wait two weeks to probably
code it in a couple of days.
And all of a sudden, I felt that
pressure are delivering to my colleagues,
because I told them I could
probably do it. Plus, I had some
intrinsic motivation in learning about
image processing. So,
altogether, I entered into a specialized
passion mode, and there you go. I
was spending every
single evening going through image
processing tutorials and trying to learn
as much as possible to be
able to create that algorithm for my
project. Now, the important point here
is that I had a safety net,
because if I would not have been able
to deliver, anyway, my colleague would
have come back from
holidays two weeks later, and he would
have managed to create a algorithm,
no problem. So, in a way,
the pressure was not that high, but
because I still wanted to impress my
colleagues, there was enough
pressure to push me into learning
mode and bring my skills one level up.
The good thing of this method
is that anybody can implement it.
Let's say that, for example, you want to
learn how to play the guitar.
Instead of just saying to yourself, I
want to learn how to play the guitar.
You can invite some
friends over for dinner and tell
them that also, you're going to play a
couple of songs in the guitar.
So, all of a sudden, the stakes are higher,
you feel that pressure, and you can enter
can enter into the
pressurized passion mode. And if you
want to keep the momentum going, you
can just keep on raising
the stakes little by little, so the
pressure is still high enough to push
you into the learning mode.
Over time, I kept on using this method
to improve my skills over and over,
and it brought me to a
point where I became fundamental for
my project team, because essentially, I
became the image processing guy,
and the algorithms I was developing,
they were being used to set actual
requirements for the
product that we're working on.
Now here, the stakes were real. They were
feeling very high, because basically,
like I mentioned, my algorithms were
being used to set requirements for the
product, meaning,
if I would do something wrong in
them, most likely the project would fail.
But that continuous
process of using pressure-ized
passion to bring my skills one level up, it
brought me to a point
where the pressure was really manageable,
and actually, there was not really
a task that felt
really difficult to do for me.
Thanks to using this method. In 2019, I was
able to land a job within
the same company, leading a small
team of data analysts of a product we're
working on. And this
all happened, because
once, I'd dare to click
on the reply button,
and it created some
pressure-ized passion that basically,
it brought me from having zero coding
skills to being able
to create some very sophisticated
algorithm. So, if you're struggling to
learn a new skill, try
entering the pressure-ized passion mode.
Find a way to raise the stakes and
hold yourself accountable.
Click the reply button, tell your
friends you'll show them what you've
learned, or even
start your own YouTube channel,
so you can share your progress with
everybody around the world.
I hope my story has inspired you to
take that very first step, and if you do
so, please let
me know in the comments below,
because I would love to read those stories.
Also, please don't forget
to leave a like and
subscribe to the channel,
and I'll see you
again next time. Bye!