Are you sick of using
the exact same layouts
for every hero section
of every website?
Well in this video, I'm going to share
with you 18 different hero variations
that you can steal to start
using in your designs today.
Let's get into it.
Now the first hero layouts that I want
to cover are those that I would classify
as Ol' Reliable.
These are layouts
that you're going to see
all the time and there's
a reason that you
see them all the time.
It's because they work in
terms of conversion, usability.
And the first and probably most common
is this classic left-right layout, right?
You've got your text and your call
to action on the left and the image
on the right.
A good example of
this is this stairs website
and you can see
especially with a nice
graphic on the right side.
It's really going to bring
this basic layout to life.
Another thing that you can do is
take that image on the right side and
stretch it to the
height of the viewport and by doing
this, it's going to create a little bit
more of a custom feel. And I
really like this example by fino.
Now, both of these
layouts can be flipped
and so rather than
left-right, you're going
right-left.
Meaning you have the
image on the left and
you have the text and
call to action on the
right.
Now, while this is a nice way to
shake it up, I don't really recommend that
you use this too
often because typically
speaking with most
languages, we read left
to right.
That's the way that we
look at websites as well.
So, If you've got the
image on the left, that's
typically going to
be the first thing that
people look at.
So unless you've got a really powerful
image that conveys your message and
your value proposition,
I wouldn't typically recommend
putting your image on the left.
But there is a good example of this here.
They still do a good job of calling
attention to the text on the right side.
So in this case, I feel
like it's kind of working.
The other thing that you can do
is again, bring that image to the full
height of the viewport.
And here's another
great example of that.
All right.
So the next one that
I want to talk about
is one that I would
classify as Old School.
And the reason that I classify this as
Old School is that something that you
would see years ago,
and it makes
websites feel outdated.
So I wouldn't really recommend this
one, but this layout is having the image
on the background and then
the text as an overlay over the top.
Now again, this can be done tastefully.
And so I don't want to say you
should never use this, but it's really easy
to kind of lose track
of the text in the image.
But one example
that I really liked of this
is this website
Secret Developers.
You can see they've gotten a really
nice image on the backdrop, but they
still are using
some bold text over
the front to bring
your focus to that text.
The one thing that
I don't like is the call
to action is really
difficult to see over
the image.
All right.
So now we're going to
talk about centered layouts.
I am actually a big
fan of centered layouts
back in college when I
was taking design classes.
My teachers would say you
should never center a line text.
It's not tasteful.
It doesn't look good.
But honestly, I think
it's kind of easy to
consume and it keeps
things looking really
nice and flow really nicely.
And so a few examples of this are just
this classic center layout where you've
got your text call to
action and then your image.
And oftentimes that
image is going to kind
of flow out of the
bottom of the viewport,
but as long as enough of that
image or video is showing, it's going to
encourage people
to scroll to see more.
And here's a great example of
this from this website, Payking.
The next one is a slight variation
of this centered layout where we're
taking the image of bringing
it above the call to action.
I personally am not
a huge fan of this
because we want to
keep that call to action as
one of the main focal
points, but there are
cases where this
can be done tastefully.
In this case, Elaster Bank does kind
of a cool graphic that comes up and
over the call to action
might be something worth looking
into and trying in your designs.
The next one that I really like is
the center line text and call to action
with a few images
floating around the size.
This is a great example here,
HomeHero where they're actually using
different like profile
pictures of happy people.
This kind of conveys
their message.
I'm a big fan of this.
I'm such a big fan of this that I've
even used in my own website, paitpro.
You can see that we've got a
couple of profile pictures with little like
text boxes popping up.
That kind of convey more about our
paitpro community for web designers.
I'm a big fan of this and you can
see that I also used a slight variation
where the video, our
promo video is showing
just a little bit on the bottom of the
viewport which is encourages people to
scroll and watch that video.
The next ones that I want to talk
about are horizontal variations and
these are horizontally aligned in
terms of the text and call to action.
I think this is a really creative
way to lay out your hero section.
You can see here we've
got the main header
to the left, the sub-header
and the call to action
to the right and then
the image down below.
A good example of this is spline.
I actually think they
do this pretty tastefully.
They've got some cool imagery and
they have a great use of hierarchy so you
know exactly
where to look.
You've got the big bold header.
You've got the subtext.
You've got a colored call to action.
They do this really, really well.
The next one is a
slight variation of that
where you're actually
taking the subtext
and moving this to the left.
I am not a fan of this
one because again,
traditionally we're
reading left to right
and we don't want people to read the
subtext before they read the main text
or value
proposition and this
kind of goes against
basic philosophy of
hierarchy because you've
got your main header in the
middle of its bigger so that should call
people's attention
a little bit more.
But when they're
reading left to right,
they're also prone to
read the sub text first.
I just don't think that this is very
user friendly but it might be something
worth trying out.
The next one is a
huge hero image
over the top and then
we've got our header
and our sub header down below.
This is kind of an
interesting layout mainly
because in the
examples that I found
they don't really
have a call to action.
However there are
occasionally websites
where you don't really
need a call to action.
They're just websites
that are built to
convey information and
so this might be layout
that you want to use
if you have a website
like that that doesn't
necessarily have a
call to action.
The next layouts that
I want to talk about
are those that I
classified as quirky.
These are ones that I wouldn't necessarily
recommend using on an everyday
basis, but they might be fun
variations to try in some of your designs.
The first one utilizes somewhat of a
background image where you've got the
text that slightly
overlays the image
and then we've got
our sub header down
to the bottom right.
This is kind of a
cool example of that.
Now with this you
want to make sure that
there's a lot of contrast
between the header
and the image and
so you're going to have
to be really careful
with what you choose.
I also sometimes see
variations where the
text overlays it would
invert to the color white.
So again this may not be the easiest
to read but it is kind of a cool way to
shake up your hero section.
The next example
is a slight variation
from what we've talked
about in some of the past
examples but you've
got your header centered
up top, you've got
an image down below
and then you've got your sub-header
and the call to action in the bottom right.
I kind of like this example because
you've got a big fat burger in the
bottom left, but you
still are utilizing hierarchy and
people are going to be able to read kind
of left, center to right.
So this one actually works
pretty well and I kind of like this.
The next example is actually
one that I'm a big fan of.
The only thing you
have to be careful of
is making sure that
this doesn't become too
overwhelming but
you've got all of your
important info to the left,
your text, call to action,
you've got an image in the
center and then you've got some
additional text or even
buttons to the right
and I really like this
example of trend.
You can see that again you're still
going to be reading left to right, big
text down to call to action.
You've got a really cool image in
the center but then on the right you
actually have buttons that are
sliders to change that image.
Again you want to be careful to not
overwhelm people with too much in your
hero section
but this is a cool variation that I
would definitely recommend trying out in
your designs.
The next example is again just a
slight change up from the ones we just
spoke about but
we've got our text and
then our call to action
kind of slanting
to the right starting
from the center and then
we've got images on the left.
Again you want to be careful using
your images on the left just because
that's what people
are probably going to see first but
there are ways to do this tastefully.
It's showing these books on the
left which I actually think in this case it
really works because
it's showing some of
what they're offering
and so I actually like
this and then
their call to action
the bottom right is a
search bar rather than
a button which again
depending on the purpose of
your website can work really well.
The next one that I'm actually a
huge fan of is this slight centered
variation but instead
of having everything centered you've
got your subtext and call to action on
a horizontal alignment
and then you've
got images to the
left and to the right.
This website puzzle is a
really cool example of this.
The images are not necessarily descriptive
but they are on brand and they're
really bright
and colorful and fun
and then I also like
that they're calling
more attention to the
call to action with the little arrow.
So this is a really cool variation
that I'm definitely going to be using.
The next one is a
variation that I'm not
super thrilled about
but they are somewhat
sticking to the
whole idea of header
to the left and then
moving to the right.
The only problem
is the header is in the
bottom left and then
they've got big images
right here in the center
kind of slanting down.
You can see in this
example here the reason
that this one is working
is because those
images are portraying what it
is that they offer or what they do.
It's the UI of their app but again
this can get a little confusing when
people are looking
they're going to start at the top
left and then go to the bottom left to
read the header
and then they're going to go to the
center to see the images and then top
right to read the
subtext and then
they're going to wander
with a call to action
and they're gonna
go to the bottom-right and so it can
get kind of overwhelming but it might
be something worth trying out.
The next variation
this is something that
I have really loved
and I'm seeing this more
often and this is using a standard
layout but instead of having imagery in a
traditional location like left, right,
center they've got it within the header
and this is a really
fun way to express more in the
main h1 of your website and like
they say, "A picture is
worth a thousand words"
and so if you're trying to
say more in the main text of
your hero section
this might be the
variation for you and I
really like this example
you can see they've
got different images between
creative agency for the ocean.
I'm obsessed with this layout.
It is a little bit more
quirky, a little bit
more out there but
if you do it in a very
conservative way, I think
it can work really well.
Now if you like this video hit the like
button and subscribe to my channel
if you haven't already
because I've got new
videos just like this
one coming out every
single week.
Plus if you're interested in applying
for our private community for web
designers where we have monthly
trainings, we share resources
and we have monthly
design competitions
with huge cash prizes be sure to click
the link down below or you can go to
paitpro.com to apply.
I hope to see you inside and
we'll catch you in the next video.
[Music].