Without a doubt, the single most
important factor to your success as a
freelancer is your confidence.
But unfortunately, confidence
is not the most exciting topic.
But before you click off this video,
I'm going to give you three very
practical and actionable tips
that you can follow to skyrocket
your confidence starting today.
Now, these things that I'm going to
share with you are very special to me
because this is what has made
the biggest difference for me
in my six-year career as a freelancer.
And I know they're going to make
a massive difference for you as well.
Now, your confidence can
be felt by everyone around you.
Your prospects, your clients,
your team members and employees.
And so as you increase
your confidence,
everything is going
to go more smoothly.
You're going to get paid more.
People are going to respect you more.
And overall, you are going to
become a more successful freelancer.
So I want to start with an
example of how confidence works.
And the best example is
the public schooling system.
I went to public school.
I went to elementary school,
junior high school or middle school.
And some people call high school college.
And the interesting thing about school
is whatever level we are at, we are
overwhelmed and
intimidated by our environment.
So on elementary school, I was
nervous about my teachers and friends and
bullies and girls
and all these things
intimidated me and they
drained my confidence.
But then I moved on to junior
high and the same thing happened.
But when I thought about maybe going
back to elementary school, it seemed
not so scary.
And so if we could
have the confidence of
our future self in
our current situation,
we would have unlimited confidence, right?
If I could have the confidence I had
in college in high school, I would be
the most confident person in the school.
And so we let our environment
and our external factors dictate our
confidence.
And so we need to keep the mindset
of how can I have the confidence of my
future self five years down the
road or 10 years down the road.
And how can I apply that
confidence to my situation today?
Now, if we boil it down to its most
simple form, truly confidence is
determined by control.
So the more control we have of a
situation, the more confident we feel.
So there's a reason that we feel
more confident around our friends and in
our own home.
But when we go out
and we're meeting new
people or we're in
different situations,
it drains our confidence because we
don't have control over the environment.
Now, in terms of freelancing, there
are really only three ways where our
clients take that
control away from us.
So if we can understand
and pinpoint these
situations and then
take that control back,
we're going to have
unlimited confidence and
you're going to be
blown away by how much
easier it is to land clients, charge
more and feel comfortable in every
single call in situation.
So the first way that clients will
take away your control and your
confidence is through finances or money.
Or in other words, if you need their
money so badly that you're desperate,
they have the control and you will be
nervous and anxious and needy and
you'll worry about every word you
say and how they perceived you.
And if you're going to close the deal
and when they take this control and
confidence away from
you, you are much less
likely to close deals
and land clients.
So you need to get this control back.
The first way you can do this is just
tell yourself that you don't care and
that you don't need this client.
Just saying that out loud is going to
get a lot of that control back to you.
The other way you can do this
is just by landing more clients.
Now, this sounds easy and I know
that it's not as easy as it sounds.
But the more clients you land,
the less depending you are on every
individual client and their paycheck.
When somebody else controls your
paycheck, you don't have the control.
The second way that clients will
rob you of control and confidence is
verbally.
Or in other words,
the way that they talk
to you and the way
that you talk to them.
In every conversation, there's somebody
that controls the conversation and
controls the frame.
And if that's not you, it is going
to completely zap your confidence.
When clients pressure us, they
talk over us, they manipulate us.
These are the ways that they are
trying to pull that control back from us.
And oftentimes they don't even realize
they're doing it, but you have to be
conscious of this and make
sure that you maintain that control.
Now, the way that you can do this is
by adjusting the way that you speak.
So for example, if a client asks
you point blank, why should I hire you
rather than you trying to explain yourself,
you should respond by saying,
I'm not really sure if you should yet.
I'm still trying to determine if
you're a good fit for us as well.
So let's talk a little bit more about
what you need and then we'll see if
we're a good fit.
So you can see by
changing that wording,
I'm not allowing them
to have that control.
And therefore, I am maintaining
my confidence in this conversation.
The other ways that you can
maintain this control is by talking slowly.
The faster you talk, the less confident
you seem and you'll be blown away by
how confident you feel if you
just slow down your speaking.
This is going to command more attention
from your prospects and it's going
to allow you more time to know what to say.
And when you know what you're going
to say, you also feel more confident.
The other thing that you can do is
ask more questions in most scenarios,
whether it is with a teacher,
whether it's with an employer,
the person that's asking the
questions is typically in charge.
And so don't allow them to
just drill you with questions.
You need to regain that frame
and start asking them questions.
And sometimes you
even need to respond
to their question
with another question.
By controlling the conversation with
questions, you can maintain that frame.
Now the third and final way that
clients and prospects can take away your
control and your confidence
is through perception.
Now this is something that I learned
from my business coach that has
completely changed
my life because
this goes beyond just
freelancing or work.
When you allow other people's perception
to control your own confidence, you
will lose every single time because
no matter what you do, no matter how
fantastic you are or popular you
are or famous you are, you can never
control the perception of somebody else.
And so if you base your confidence
off of how other people feel about you,
you will never have control and
you will never have confidence.
So instead you have to look to your
own perception of yourself and make that
the only thing that matters.
So when you're in a call with a
prospect, stop worrying about how they're
going to perceive you and
what they think about you.
And if they think you sound professional
or if they think you sound like you
don't know what you're saying, you
need to let all of those things go and
only worry about how
you feel about yourself.
Do you feel like you're being professional
and honest and are you proud of
the way that you're acting and if so,
you can pull a ton of confidence from
that.
And the nice part is
you have 100% complete
control over how you
feel about yourself.
You can't control what other people
think and feel about you, but you can
always control how you feel within.
So remember these three things.
You've got financial control, you've
got verbal control and you've got
perception control.
If you can control
these three aspects,
you are going to have
unlimited confidence.
You're going to know exactly what to
say and people are going to be really
impressed with the
type of person and
freelancer and
professional that you are.
Now, if you enjoyed this
video, hit that like button.
It's not going to
control my confidence,
but it does make
me feel pretty nice.
And if you have any other tips that
help you feel confident as a freelancer,
as a professional, please
drop them in the comments.
But you say no that they're
going to help somebody else.
Thanks for watching and
we'll catch you in the next video.