First of all, before this video starts,
I would like to give a big thank you
to all of my new subscribers.
I was not expecting even one
subscriber to be honest, so to wake up this
morning and see a
hundred people following me,
I was a bit surprised. So thank you
so much for liking my content, and I
hope you stick around in the
future for even more content.
About two days ago, I gave my final
presentation on my senior project, which
fingers crossed went really well,
meaning that in a couple of weeks
now, I will finally graduate college.
I mean, it just feels so great to finally
be free of homework assignments,
projects, and free from the goddamn
elevator that breaks every two weeks.
Finally, I'm able to do
whatever I want as a free adult.
Who are you? Yeah, Hi. Did
you check your bank account?
What do you mean, check?
Just check your bank account.
Oh, yeah. Yeah, I should probably
get a job. It's kind of funny how college
just kind of takes your
money in the after four years,
throws you out to the streets, and
says, "Good luck on finding a job!"
And, you know, please, when you get
money, pay us even more. It's like the
first couple thousand dollars
were not enough for them, but I do
want to agree that college does not have
to baby you through all the steps of life.
Finding a career is something
that you have to do all on your own.
But anyway, because I'm soon going
to need to find a job, I wanted to spend
some time and
research a little bit about
the possible jobs
there are out there.
Because one of the beautiful things
about being a programmer is that you're
not really limited to
just working in one field,
which is amazing because
imagine if you're majoring in art
history, I'm so sorry, but here we
out put down your paint brushes.
No, I don't think art historians paint.
Put down your art textbooks. What I
mean by this is that as an art historian,
I think the only place you really
work in is a museum or something.
As a programmer, however, you have
many different fields to choose from. You
could work as a programmer in
the medical field. You could work as a
programmer in the finance field.
You can work in robotics, in avionics,
heck, you could even work at Roblox.
You're laughing, but I kid you
not, that's where the real money is.
Look it up, I swear. And so today
I'm going to spend a little bit time going
through various different fields and
figuring out what they are and what it
takes to become whatever
it is you're going to become.
Disclaimer, I spent a little bit of
time researching this so that I don't
sound like an idiot. But if I do get
something wrong, please let me know in
the comments.
After a little bit of researching, I've
compiled a bit of information about
some of the most popular jobs there are.
And the most basic jobs that usually
pop up are computer programmers and
software engineers.
Now you might be thinking, aren't
those the same thing? I mean, they surely
sound like the same thing.
I mean, a software engineer just
kind of sounds like a fancier version of a
computer programmer.
Oh, what do you do for a job? Oh, I
write computer programs. Oh, cool, cool.
What do you do for a job?
I engineer software.
Oh, okay. But there is a difference though.
So let me first explain what a
computer programmer is.
A computer programmer at the most
basic level is someone who can write,
modify, and test code.
Although we all know that you're
probably going to spend like 10% of the
time writing code.
The other 90% of the time baying
your head against the wall because
something isn't working.
Don't you just love being a programmer?
You should generally be proficient
in at least one type of language
and have a basic knowledge of computer
science principles. So we help us to
see what's trending
at the time in the programming world
to see what language you should learn.
And now we have the
software engineer. To put it simply,
they're not only responsible for
writing the code,
they're responsible for coming up
with the concept of the code. You can
think of this as a mechanic
is able to put a car together with
a bunch of parts, but a mechanical.
engineer can understand
the individual functionality of each
part as well as probably design the car
from scratch himself.
These two fields work together in
a way where the software engineer
spends time developing
a specific software
and then works
together with a bunch of
computer programmers
to make the completed version of the
software. And now the most important
part, salary. According to
the Bureau of Labor Statistics, computer
programmers earn an average of 93k
a year, which is pretty good
if I say so myself. While a software
engineer averages at 120k a year, but
do not confuse this
with the starting salary. On average
for a starting salary, I'm seeing
online a mix between
60k a year or 70k a year at a
starting salary. If you're lucky, you could
get something higher than that
and if you get something lower than that.
Anyway, let's move away from these
really broad career
topics. And I want to talk a little
bit about these three jobs that I keep
seeing pop up,
which let's start with front end
development. Front end development works at
the front end of
applications, which is
where the UI exists.
You're dealing with the
buttons, you're dealing
with the images, you're dealing
with the layout and the design of the
website itself. Now,
this point has seemed like
something really difficult, but in fact, it
actually is pretty hard to
create a really
good user interface.
What is going on here?
What am I looking
at? And so if you're
going to be working with the UI,
it's definitely going to require a bit of
more creative
psychology. And that's essentially all
that front end development is. You're
going to need to know
a little bit of HTML or CSS. Now,
moving on to, I wouldn't call the opposite
of it, but at the
opposite end of front end, you have
the back end, the back end deals with
the functionality of the
front end. So you have the buttons,
you have the very cool, the animated
portfolio website,
but do the buttons work. Do you need
a database that you need to search? All
of this is the
responsibility of the backend developer.
For this, you would mainly learn
maybe JavaScript. There's
also a bunch of other languages out there.
You have the love child, the full
stack developer,
full stack developers work in both front
end and back end development. They
are the Jack of all
trades. Now, let's talk
about salaries. This
is where I got a bit
confused looking up online
because they're giving a bunch of
different variety of salaries. Like, and
I'm just going to say
that I think they're
all within the range
of 100k. Again, not
the starting salary,
but the possible future salary.
Going even deeper down the rabbit hole,
There're even more
specific specializations.
Cyber security is a field
where you're working
with encryption and making
sure that data in websites or
applications is not get leaked to hackers.
There's also cloud computing.
This is a field where essentially
working on delivering different types of
computer resources to
different people over the Internet.
Another important field is data
scientists, which are people
who work on a load of data that is
given to them and try to make sense of it.
The reason I'm able
to look up all the salaries is because
some data scientists did their job.
And there was just so
many more specialized jobs out
there that if I try to put them all in one
video, I would be sitting
here for an hour and that's just
going to be too long to edit. So I'm not
going to go any further.
I'm going to link some pages of
where I found all this information. If you
want to take a look at
some more fields that there are.
But for now, I'm going to move on to two
fields that I find
incredibly interesting myself.
The first is game development. Now, this
career in itself has many
different paths. You could
think of it as all of the different
specializations
that I said before
where in game development, you could
either work as a game programmer, a
game designer. And most
importantly, I would say you could
work as an indie game developer. You
don't have to work sitting
there nine to five, killing your
eyes, killing your back, killing your
social life. Instead, you
could work from home and develop
games on your own or maybe in small teams.
Technology is getting
so advanced in game development
that this is fully possible. And I think
it's a lot more comfortable.
And lastly, one of the most in demand
fields there are right now is AI and
machine learning development.
Now, I know you've probably seen it
everywhere. How AI is on the rise. And
yeah, AI is getting
incredibly powerful. Just in the last
couple of months, there's been so much
progress and development
in machine learning and AI that honestly,
it really scared me for a bit. But
then I sat back and
realized this isn't the Terminator.
I'll be back. And that's the thing. I
don't think many people
realize that AI is not the supercomputer
that can think on its own. Well,
it actually is kind of that, but it's
still just a bunch of code. We're not
at the level yet,
where AI can effectively think on its
own without having some human sitting
there telling it what
it's doing wrong or right. Now, this
is a field that is on the rise, but the
most popular language at
the moment to do AI development and
machine learning in is Python, but you
can use it for variety
of different languages
as well. And I would
say for this, you
definitely need a bit of math.
You also have to understand some
more in depth computer science concepts to
understand how to
program a neural network, but nothing
code academy in a couple of YouTube
videos cannot teach you.
I will be making another video going
more into depth about AI. So subscribe
if you are interested
in that. And yeah, that's pretty much
some of the main jobs that I've looked
into. I do want to
close this video off by saying one
last thing. And I think this is the most
important life lesson
that I have been told. See, when it
comes to finding a job, people get this
misconception that they
have to look for their dream job or
the job that they're going to absolutely
love to be in every
single day of the week. And that's
just a bit of naive thinking. I'm not
saying that it's impossible
to find your dream jobs. There is
multiple examples online out there where
people find their dream jobs,
but some people just don't really
know right away what their dream job
is, or some people
just want to dabble in a bunch of fields.
And so I feel like instead of
saying that you should find
your dream job, you should rather
find a job that you tolerate at the very
least. You see, even in a
dream job, you're going to have bad days.
You're going to have days where
you wish you can just
jump out the window. And that's
fine because a job is a job. There's the
saying you work to live,
not live to work. I'm going to try and
do a bunch of different projects, you
know, and post them on
this channel to basically just get
a feel for what I personally and I'm
interested in. And I highly
encourage you to do the same
thing. Anyway, thank you for watching.
Once again, thank you
so much to all of my new
subscribers. And
yeah, see you next time.