If I had to build a brand
new app tomorrow,
would I build my backend
in TypeScript or Go?
The honest answer is probably a
little bit of both. Let's talk about it.
Before I get into exactly
where I would use
which, let's first talk
about these languages for
backend development and
how they sort of compare.
So starting over in the
Go world, Go is super fast
to write, super easy to
write, super fast in runtime,
and it is extremely
easy to vertically scale.
The language is super
efficient, it's garbage
collected, which TypeScript
is too, but the garbage
collector in Go, I don't
know how they made it
work so well, but it
works really, really well.
So, Go is super easy
to scale vertically, which
just means that if we
have like one CPU instance
of it running, if we
just scale up that CPU
to be more and more powerful, we can deal
with any amount of requests super easily.
Go is a super efficient language,
and it's super easy to scale.
So it's fast, scalable,
and easy to write.
Great stuff. Now we Go
over to the TypeScript world,
it does not scale
vertically. I know yet no.
I'm not entertaining that
TypeScript does not scale vertically.
Now you can make
TypeScript scale of course,
but that is going to require
either serverless or k8s.
And k8s are Kubernetes
that's effectively
horizontally scaling,
which means that we're
creating more and
more Docker images.
So we can split these horizontally,
which means we make more
instances of our app
versus in Go. It's really easy
to just keep one instance
of the app and just make
that one instance
bigger and bigger.
So that's the sort of difference
is that in TypeScript world,
we need to either
horizontally scale or we need
to scale via serverless
or something like that.
Then in TypeScript, we're going to
get solid performance. I mean, it's not
groundbreaking, not
super fast, certainly much,
much slower than Go and
much less efficient than Go,
but it's still Good
enough performance that
especially if you're
really just only doing
IO type stuff, you're
never going to feel it.
If you're just reading and
writing from a database,
TypeScript is print
plenty, plenty fast, and
there's no issues. But
when you get into more
complicated CPU heavy
stuff, you're going to want
to be using Go. Now also
in the TypeScript world,
it is super, super
easy to write.
I think both of these languages
are pretty easy to write,
but I think TypeScript
is even more intuitive to
write than Go. Go has
some little quirks to it
that are kind of weird and
TypeScript is pretty much
become the dominant
language for borderline
everything at this point,
frontend and backend
for better for worse,
JavaScript is everywhere.
So it's very easy to write
no issues, you're going
to have no issues hiring
for anything like that.
That of course, the TypeScript
package ecosystem is pretty incredible.
There is huge amounts of innovation happening in the TypeScript world all the time.
Nextjs, Prisma, Remix, TRPC, all of this stuff
is constantly changing, growing, evolving,
and you're not getting that
as much in the Go world.
There is exciting stuff happening in
the Go world. Pocket base is super cool.
And there's a lot of really important
stuff being built with an in Go,
but it's not quite as
flashy and not quite as
big and crazy and well supported as TypeScript
just because more people use TypeScript.
Go is less popular and it's
more slept on in a lot of ways.
So you're going to get better
support over in the TypeScript world.
But with those two things
put next to each other,
I mean, it seems like you can get a
little more ease of use in TypeScript,
but on an objective level,
Go does seem better.
It seems like you're
going to get a faster, easier
to scale cheaper
runtime for your backend.
So it seems like a no brainer
just use Go. But it's not that simple.
Applications are
not built in a vacuum.
And there's something
we need to think about
when architecting these
things is how is this all
going to work together.
And maybe 10 years ago,
it would have been
really easy to just say, oh,
just use Go if we're
just going to be sending
requests down to a front
end on all we need to
do is that yeah, just use
Go because we're going
to have a client side,
we're going to have our
client side code, which
can just make requests to
a singular Go server. And
then we'll send it back down.
No issues. But
things have changed.
And we've got some crazy new
stuff over in the TypeScript world.
Specifically, these meta frameworks, the
Nextjs, Nuxtjs, Solid start, Sveltekit,
these frameworks
have changed the game,
these server side rendering
TypeScript frameworks have made a
huge difference. And I
think for me, the sort of
draw bounding line
between these two, to be
completely honest, is how
close do I want my backend
to be much with how
close do I want my front
and backend to be? Do I
want these two to be super
interconnected? And I
want them to link borderline
one to one, then I
want to use TypeScript.
And if I want them to be
fairly disconnected and how my
backend be kind of
agnostic and be able to use
be used on any
platform or anything,
I want it to be in Go. So
the first thing I'm going to say
about using Go is I would
always use Go if I need a
standalone backend.
So that means that I'm
just spinning up a
rest API that is going to
send and receive responses
over HTTP or create
like a graphQL endpoint
that's going to send
responses over the
graphQL protocol.
So if I was creating a standalone
backend, I would do it in Go.
For the reasons I listed
above the scalability,
performance, all that
stuff, it just can't be beat.
If you're not getting
huge DX improvements,
I wouldn't do it in Go.
If you're basically just
creating a rest API on
an objective level, Go is
better and it's faster. And for
me, that's what I would go with.
But you're not always going to
be creating a standalone backend.
So when would I use TS? Well,
that would be when my frontend and
backend are tightly
coupled. And then that is
going to be in parentheses,
Nextjs, Nuxtjs, Sveltekit, Solid Start, etc.,
So if I would if I
were using one of these
frameworks, if I was using
a meta framework, and I
was basically just wanted
read and write out of
a user's table, I would
use TS for my backend.
And if I was going to
write a TS backend, I
would write it in one of
these frameworks, these
frameworks would be my
backend, I would not
make a separate instance
for it, not make an Express
server, a Nest server,
whatever, I would make
it in Next or Nuxt. So what
do I mean by tightly
coupled? And that basically
just means I want to
be able to call a function
on my frontend, and
then do basically that exact
thing on the back. So what
are some examples of this?
A really Good one
would be just I need to
update a user's settings.
So update user settings.
If I want to go to my
website, and I want to go
to their profile page,
and I want to update
their email notifications
or something like that,
that's tight coupling,
because I'm just going
to be basically making
a request to an endpoint,
that's gonna be like,
Hey, switch this update this
and then send me back
down that did update it.
Great. And now what I
can do is by tight coupling
these two, I get all
the benefits of a shared
language, which allows
me to use a framework
like tRPC to link
between the two of them.
Because the key here,
when we're writing our
frontends and backends,
we have our client over here.
So this is going to be our client. And
then over here, we have our server.
So our client and our
server are over here.
And in a traditional model, there's a
pretty strong line in between these two,
especially if we're using like a
single page app or something like that,
the client is going to send
requests over to the server, and the
server is going to send down responses.
And this is going to be request response.
req, res, HTTP.
So we have one way of doing this, which is
going to be a request and response over HTTP.
If these two are going to be
super detached, and all I was
going to do was just
communicate between the two
with requests and response
and HTTP, this would
be a Go server for me,
I would want to you get
the performance
and scalability of Go.
But where this gets interesting is if I'm
going to be using something like tRPC.
Now, what is tRPC, if you're not familiar
with it, this is a brand new TypeScript
package that basically makes a
front and backend development.
It makes full stack development stupid,
easy to do. It's become kind of the hit
new thing online. It's gotten super popular,
super fast.
And it allows your front and your
backend to communicate with ease.
So it basically allows you to share
types from the front to the backend.
So if I was going to use tRPC,
this would be pure TypeScript for me.
Because what I can do is I can share
these types from my server to my client,
it's all strongly typed. And
that is a super powerful thing.
And it's absolutely something you
should look into. If you have an app
that's not complex enough
to really need anything
more to this, if all your
app is going to be doing
is basically just
glorified crud, if it's like a,
it's like an accounting
management app, you need
to go in and you need
to read from a user's table
and then get their profiles
out. And then you need
to see how many accounts
they have. And then within
these accounts, you
need to update some data,
read some tables,
all this basic stuff.
tRPC is going to be great
for that because they're super
tightly coupled. And you can share
your types from the front to the backend
and it can make full stack
development a breeze.
It makes it super easy for anyone to
write an entire app all by themselves.
Versus if you wanted to do versus if
you wanted to do that with like having
a separate Go backend,
that would get a little
harder because you're
not going to be able to
share those types. And you're going to have
to sort of deal with things going over HTTP.
It's hard to describe if you've
never used tRPC before
and next week I'm going to be using it
a lot live, but definitely Go look it up.
There's a million videos on it,
but go take a look at this and
sort of see how you can connect
these two with strong typing.
And when we're using these new
frameworks like Next
and Nuxt and all this stuff,
it's really easy to host
these in a way that we
kind of it edges out a
lot of these issues that
we have with typescript.
So the scalability is a
big problem. So we need
to be using something
like serverless. But
the platform, Vercel,
which is where you're generally
speaking going to be hosting this,
it's just innately serverless.
It's going to set up and do all
the serverless config for you.
And there's no
issues whatsoever.
So basically, anytime
you have tight coupling
and you can get away
with using a framework like
Next or Nuxt, Sveltekit
or whatever for your
entire app, do it. If you
don't need a separate
backend, don't make
one. Now I know this sounds
like I'm ragging on Go.
And yeah, I do really
like Go. And in my case,
for Insiderwiz, I use
both typescript and Go
for my backend. I have,
on a real live app right
here, this is running
both typescript and Go.
And the reason for that
is because the tightly
coupled stuff, which is
going to be my user
management, my subscription
management, my like
basic stuff in my database,
that is all going to be managed
with Typescript and Nextjs.
So I have a Nextjs
server doing all that.
It makes it really easy. But then if I
want to deal with more complicated stuff,
that's more detached, that doesn't
really care about my application state,
then I use Go, I use Go for the API
that manages all of this form data,
all this stuff, all the financial
data you see on the site,
I use Go because I need higher
performance to deal with this massive,
these massive quantities
of data and all that stuff.
So really, I think
where this comes in is
first of all, I would use Go
and a standalone backend.
Second of all, I would
use it in a place where
performance matters,
where each request is going
to have heavy CPU compute
and stuff like concurrency
and yeah, stuff like
concurrency actually starts
to matter. If that doesn't
matter to your app, if
again, if you're just reading and
writing out of a user table or something,
then just use a typescript app.
But if you want to use something
more performant, you
need to do something
a little crazier, which
in the real world,
you probably will more
often than not, a real app
is going to end up needing
something this crazy,
it's going to need something
more serious, you're going to get
beyond just crud in a to-do app.
That's when languages like Go
start to become really valuable.
When things go beyond just the trivial
reading and writing out of a database,
that's when I would
move over to here.
So hopefully that answers
the question on where
I would use which. I know
this was all over the place,
which is unfortunate,
but this is kind of a hard
topic to structure because
this is very much a feel thing.
Telling you when and where to
use something is a hard thing to do.
It's hard to intelligently
and clearly not.
I don't want to just lead you
astray on this and just be like,
give you a definitive,
always use this, always use that.
But then when you
don't give a definitive,
it gets kind of wishy-washy
because I'm well,
basically my thesis is,
well, they're both good,
you know, just use what
you think you should use.
But that doesn't
mean anything until you
have the experience
with it. So I think what I
would do is I would look
at really give TypeScript
a shot, see how all of these
frameworks work and all this stuff.
And then once you've understood that,
then when you need something that's more
standalone and you need
that higher performance,
go into the Go world.
Now, if you're not a full stack
developer and you just need to be making
APIs and you don't care
at all about the frontend
and it needs to be
completely agnostic,
then I would look at Go
because there's no real
reason to bottleneck
yourself with TypeScript
if you're not going to
get benefits out of sharing
types between the front and
the backend and all that stuff.
If sharing code isn't
going to help you,
then don't do it. So
again, hopefully that helps.
If you enjoyed, make sure that
you like, subscribe, do all that stuff,
got brand new stuff coming all
the way through the 28th of February
every single day. And
yeah, that's about it.
Have a great day.